Alright, בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody. We're on דף קנ"א, Daf Kuf
Nun Alef, 151, and we pick up about four lines in where
it says בהמה, Behema, 1, 2, 3, five lines down, last word
on the line. If you remember, we're dealing with the person of
somebody says all my נכסים, nechasim, all my property or possessions goes
to such a person, whether he's a שכיב מרע shchiv mera or
not a שכיב מרע, shchiv mera, and the question is what types
of objects are included. So we said whether it's land or whether
it's chattel, even if it's שטרות, shtarot, even if it's cash, okay,
all of those things we learned because the משניות mishnayot use the
word נכסים nechasim in such a general and inclusive sense. So we're
going to continue to see what is included and what actually maybe
isn't included. So let's finish this up. בהמה, Behema, five lines down
in דף קנ"א עמוד א', Daf Kuf Nun Alef Amud Alef, איקרי
נכסיי. itkrei nechasai. So בהמה, behema, animals, like you might think livestock,
you know, they're not, they're inanimate, so maybe they're not in the
same category, no those are also נכסים. nechasim. דתנן: Ditnan: המקדיש נכסיו,
hamakdish nechasav, somebody who says I am sanctifying my נכסים, nechasim, my
possessions,
and
והיתה בהן בהמה, vehayta bahen behema, and there were animals amongst his
property, so ראוי לגבי מזבח re'ui legabei mizbeach and some of it
is even fit to bring as a sacrifice. So what do we
say? Normally when you say I'm sanctifying, you say I'm sanctifying my
possessions, so your house and your car and you know your table
and everything, they go to the בית הבדק, Beis HaBedek, they get
sold and the proceeds go to the general upkeep of the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. But how about your cow that doesn't have a
blemish? Does that go to the בית הבדק Beis HaBedek or does
when you say מקדיש, makdish, maybe with a cow you mean I'm
going to bring it as a קרבן? korban? Can the same word
that applied for ninety-eight percent of your property mean a donation to
the בית הבדק, Beis HaBedek, for the two percent that is the
cows and the sheep that don't have blemish, would that same statement
turn them into a קרבן korban or not? Right? It's an interesting
question. Would you like to divide the application of that one word
of I'm sanctifying my possessions? So it says,
so it says like this, so it says, זכרים, zcharim, so
if they are males and the male ones can be an עולה.
olah. Now our גירסא girsa here is עולה, olah, but actually the
גירסא girsa which is corrected by the ב"ח Bach in the משנה
mishna is ימכרו לצורכי עולות. yimacheru letzorchei olot. What you do is
you take like this: I've got this nice unblemished male cow or
sheep, and technically according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma here, it's
a debate in the משנה, mishna, what since when I say מקדיש,
makdish, since it means that for my house and my car you
mean that I'm selling it the proceeds go to the בית הבדק,
Beis HaBedek, for this cow the same thing is true, it's going
to the בית הבדק Beis HaBedek on the one hand. On the
other hand,
it seems inappropriate that something that was given to הקדש hekdesh and
that could have been brought as a קרבן korban is not going
to be brought as a קרבן, korban, it's just going to go
to בית הבדק. Beis HaBedek. So what we do is we say,
is there anybody who needs to bring an עולה? olah? Joe, I
heard you needed to bring an עולה. olah. I got this animal
here that is הקדש hekdesh for בית הבדק, Beis HaBedek, okay, I
am going to like sell it to you, so you give me
the hundred dollars for it, that hundred dollars now becomes, you know,
it's sort of like you redeem it, that hundred dollars now goes
to the בית הבדק Beis HaBedek treasury, you now have it and
now it's no longer קדוש kadosh because you redeemed it. But now
what you're going to do is you're going to sanctify it as
an עולה olah and bring it as an עולה. olah. So both
get accomplished. בית הבדק Beis HaBedek gets the cash value of the
animal, which is the type of הקדש hekdesh we're assuming you did
because that's the הקדש hekdesh you did for the rest of your
property, and the animal that was fit for being brought to the
מזבח mizbeach is eventually going to be brought into the מזבח mizbeach
because it was sold to somebody who's going to use it for
that purpose. Do you have to do that? In other words, there's
nobody who raises his hand, so you have to just hang out
with the cow until you find somebody? Yeah, it's a good question,
like what would you do בדיעבד? bedieved? I mean, the basic rule
is it's קדוש kadosh for בית הבדק. Beis HaBedek. There's another, which
is why, you know, your money is to redeem it. Right, but
like the idea is that anything that was fit לגבי מזבח, legabei
mizbeach, you know, we don't, we want to make sure that it
gets to the מזבח. mizbeach. So like I don't know what we
would do בדיעבד. bedieved. Okay, so ימכרו לצורכי עולות, yimacheru letzorchei olot,
ונקבות, unekevot, and female animals which you can't bring an עולה, olah,
ימכרו לצורכי זבחי שלמים, yimacheru letzorchei zivchei shelamim, are sold for the
purpose of a שלמים. shelamim. Now males could also be a שלמים,
shelamim, but again we would
assume that a generic sanctity means fully to the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, so fully to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is more true
in a case of an עולה olah where it all gets burnt
on the altar than a שלמים shelamim which the owners eat the
meat. So we're going to first translate it to mean עולה olah
and if עולה olah is impossible, it'll mean שלמים. shelamim. But again
according to this approach, it's all really בית הבדק, Beis HaBedek, it's
just that you ensure that the animals eventually find their way to
the מזבח. mizbeach. These are all personal עולות olot and personal שלמים.
shelamim. Correct. Okay, so now that is, so you see anyway the
point though being, the guy said I מקדיש makdish my נכסים nechasim
and it includes בהמה. behema. So the word נכסים nechasim includes livestock.
Oh okay, so that's what it says. עופות Ofos איקרו נכסי. ikru
nechasai. Similarly, birds are called נכסים. nechasim. Okay, דתניא, detanya, המקדיש נכסיו,
hamakdish nechasav, היו בהן דברים הראויים לגבי מזבח. hayu vahen devarim harauyim
legabei mizbeiach.
So it goes on and it says, you know, there's things, you're
sanctifying your property, so it goes to the בדק הבית. Bedek Habayis.
Amongst them are things that could go on the altar, and here
that includes יינות שמנים, yeinos shemanim, wine and oil, that's also can
go on the altar. Okay, ועופות, ve'ofos, and birds, birds could also
be brought as sacrifices. Okay, so and then it says what you
do with them. So it's the same type of משנה, Mishnah, and
the point being that even though you said the generic word נכסים,
nechasim, it includes even your cows and sheep and your birds and
all of those are included in נכסים. nechasim. So what type of
הקדש hekdesh are they? Are they לבית בדק הבית le-Bedek Habayis and
then you have to redeem them and make sure they get to
the altar? Or are they directly קדוש kadosh למזבח? lamizbeiach? That's the
issue that are discussed in that משנה. Mishnah. But for us what's
relevant is that they're included in the word נכסים. nechasim. Okay, so
now we go on. So so far everything is in נכסים. nechasim.
Is there anything that's not included in נכסים? nechasim? Okay, it's interesting
that we haven't mentioned, did we mention explicitly slaves? I mean slaves
were included even in the word מטלטלין metaltalin or קרקע karka from
that previous משנה. Mishnah. But did we say explicitly that they were
included in the word נכסים? nechasim? We did? Yes, I think so,
no? We said עבדא איקרו נכסי? avda ikru nechasai? חזקה כל נכסיו.
chazaka kol nechasav. Yeah, 'cause it started כל נכסיו עבדו. kol nechasav
avdo. Okay, it's interesting that you would have thought that like slaves,
which are like human beings, would be נכסים nechasim and animals would
not be נכסים. nechasim. But maybe anyway we just wanted to point
out that this word in all these משניות mishnayot is used generically
and is used for all these different types of things. Is there
anything that is not נכסים? nechasim? So let's keep on going. תפילין
איקרי נכסי. tefillin ikri nechasai. So let's say your תפילין, tefillin, maybe
you'd say מצוה mitzvah objects are not your property? I mean technically
you own your תפילין, tefillin, you own your לולב, lulav, but you
know because it's a מצוה mitzvah object maybe at least in the
way you conceptualize it it's not like standard property that I own,
right? So maybe put it in a... nope, not true. תפילין Tefillin
are called נכסים. nechasim. דתניא, Detanya, המקדיש נכסיו, hamakdish nechasav,
if somebody sanctifies his נכסים, nechasim, מעלים לו תפילין ma’alim lo tefillin
and he's got תפילין tefillin there, so they're also holy. Now what
does מעלים ma'alim mean? So there's two interpretations. רבינו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom,
it means you take it away from him. Okay, I'm very sorry,
I know you have a מצוה mitzvah to put on תפילין, tefillin,
that's your problem, it's not our problem. We're the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, we're coming to collect, give us your תפילין, tefillin, that's also
sold. Okay, so that's what he says by, you know, that's one
way of מעלים, ma'alim, you take it away from him. The רשב"ם
Rashbam means that is you evaluate, you estimate, you assess, excuse me,
the value of the תפילין tefillin and therefore you tell him, you
know, you better come up with five hundred dollars to redeem your
תפילין tefillin so that you could keep on wearing them. So it's
the same point except rather than saying we take it away, it's
saying we basically pressure him to redeem them so that he'll have
them in order to wear them. But one way or the other,
when he's מקדיש makdish his נכסים, nechasim, it includes this תפילין. tefillin.
All right, and there's a lot of reasons you could say not
anyway, meaning forget the word נכסים, nechasim, you could just say of
course you wouldn't have wanted to be מקדיש makdish his תפילין tefillin
then he wouldn't be able to do the מצוה, mitzvah, you know.
But why don't we say of course he wouldn't want to be
מקדיש makdish his car? Then he wouldn't be able to drive to
the store or his house, he wouldn't have a place to live.
That's not our problem, you said you were מקדיש makdish your נכסים,
nechasim, so you're left without a home or food or תפילין tefillin
or טלית, tallis, whatever, you'll have to figure it out. But you
were מקדיש makdish all of your נכסים. nechasim. So תפילין tefillin are
called נכסים. nechasim. Okay, now איבעיא להו. ibaya lehu. So now all
of those were straight statements, that's obvious to all of us, from
all these משניות mishnayot that it's all נכסים. nechasim. There's one thing
we're not sure whether it's נכסים nechasim or not. What is it?
ספר תורה Sefer Torah מאי? mai? How about a תורה Torah scroll?
Why should that be different? Okay, it's a מצוה mitzvah object, okay,
but you own it and why's it different than
תפילין? tefillin? Okay, so the word tells you why it might be
different. כיון דלא מזדבן, keivan d'lo mizdaben,
since you're not allowed to sell it, ואסור
לזבוני, va'asur lezabunei, so you're not allowed to sell a ספר תורה
Sefer Torah scroll except under certain circumstances. So it's an object that
can't be sold. לאו נכסי הוא? lav nechasai hu? It's not called
נכסים? nechasim? Maybe נכסים nechasim only refers to things that you have
a certain ownership over, can treat like property, like an object of
value because you could sell it and get the proceeds.
Is that why we say it's not נכסים? nechasim? או דלמא, O
dilma, or do we say, כיון דמזדבן keivan d'mizdaben ללמוד תורה ולישא
אשה, lilmod Torah ule'isha isha, there are two points you're allowed to
sell a ספר תורה: Sefer Torah: if you need to use the
proceeds in order to go to ישיבה yeshiva and go learn, or
if you need to get married. So in those, therefore נכסי הוא,
nechasai hu, therefore it should be called נכסים. nechasim. תיקו. Teiku. We
don't know. Okay, so here's the first thing we think might not
be נכסים nechasim and it seems like it might be a combination
of the fact that it's both a מצוה mitzvah object, but that
wasn't enough as we saw by תפילין, tefillin, but it's a מצוה
mitzvah object that you don't even have control over, like you can't
even like sell to get the proceeds. So really it's something that's
there to be used for the מצוה, mitzvah, it's never there to,
never treated as property. Okay, on the other hand, under certain exceptions...
On the other hand, then there's certain exceptions I'm allowed to, maybe
those exceptions are enough to say that I do see it as
something that is a piece, that is property. Okay? Even though those
are the exceptions and not the rule. The רשב"ם Rashbam has an
interesting read of help also to draw the line between this and
תפילין. Tefillin. Right. If you look at the רשב"ם Rashbam he says,
ספר תורה מי מקרי נכסי כתפילין דמי? Sefer Torah mi mikrei nechasai
k'tefillin dami? Is it like תפילין Tefillin that it is? או דילמא
תפילין היינו טעמא דהוי מלבוש? O dilma tefillin hainu ta'ama de'havei malbush?
Now this isn't in the גמרא Gemara at all, but he says
maybe an extra thing that adds to תפילין Tefillin being called נכסים
nechasim is the fact that you wear it. So it's like a
type of a clothing, I mean religious clothing, but a clothing. Okay?
אבל ספר תורה היא אבל ספר מצוה היא ולא נכסי דאף על
פי שיכול למוכרה לא נכסי לא נכסה לא נכסי. Aval sefer Torah
hi aval sefer mitzvah hi v'lo nechasai d'af al pi she'yachol l'mochra
lo nechasai lo nachsa lo nechasai.
Even though you could sell it fundamentally it's a מצוה mitzvah object.
So rather than saying the reason it's not נכסים nechasim is because
the ability to sell it is an exception and not the rule
and it's like it's a מצוה mitzvah object plus fundamentally you can't
sell it, he says no, the inability to sell it is not
relevant because there are times you're allowed to sell it. What makes
it not נכסים nechasim is the fact that it's a מצוה mitzvah
object that is only a מצוה mitzvah object, isn't like a type
of clothing like תפילין Tefillin is. So the consequence of that would
be, well what about other מצוה mitzvah objects? What? Exactly! לולב, Lulav,
שופר, Shofar, other מצוה mitzvah objects, right? So you're allowed to sell
them, but they're not like pieces of clothing. I mean a לולב's
Lulav only function is to shake. It has no other purpose than
as a מצוה mitzvah object. So from the way the רשב"ם Rashbam
frames it, that might also be in the ספר תורה Sefer Torah
category. He downplays the גמרא'ס Gemara's issue about not being able to
sell them and emphasizes its מצוה mitzvah object identity. There could be
also a conceptual difference in terms of where it's coming from. The
תורה'ס Torah's like God's תורה, Torah, right, exactly. It's like תורת השם,
Torat Hashem, right, exactly. Look, there's other differences as well because, you
know, because הלכתית, halachically, a לולב Lulav or a שופר Shofar or
whatever, they're called תשמישי מצוה, tashmishei mitzvah, מצוה mitzvah objects. Okay? And
the basic point is that they don't have any קדושה kedusha and
when it's not the מצוה mitzvah time for them, you can basically
discard them. You're not supposed to do it in a way that
חס ושלום chas v'shalom is degrading, but you wrap your לולב Lulav
in a bag and a separate bag, you don't throw it out
with the chicken bones and you just wrap it in a bag
and you throw it out. Okay? Whereas תפילין Tefillin and ספר תורה
Sefer Torah and מזוזה Mezuzah because they have God's name in them
are considered תשמישי קדושה, tashmishei kedusha, objects of holiness. Okay? And those
things you'd have to put in גניזה genizah and other types of
things. So the very fact that they have קדושה kedusha is another
reason to say it's not like just totally your object, right? So
it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara didn't raise that point as well.
But your point is also, so that's a הלכתית halachic distinction. Your
point I was thinking about as well also, just the way you
label it. Right? I mean, do you think about it, this is
God's תורה Torah and it's a physical writing of it, but it's
God's תורה. Torah. It's not just an object that we use in
a מצוה, mitzvah, right? So yeah, absolutely. Okay. But that distinction would
put תפילין Tefillin in the same category as a ספר תורה, Sefer
Torah, right? Except that the גמרא Gemara although again, I think what
David is saying and I agree with him a little bit. First
of all, you have the difference of whether you can sell it
or not. But the other thing is that
yeah, the תפילין Tefillin have in it pieces of God's תורה, Torah,
but the object is still
seen, I think the way we relate to the objects is different.
The object of the תפילין Tefillin is basically a מצוה mitzvah object
that has in it little pieces of parchment, whereas the ספר תורה
Sefer Torah itself is more directly, if you were to ask what
object do we think sort of is a, I mean you don't
like talking this way because it's a little bit of עבודה זרה
avodah zarah ish, but anyway, but you know what object do we
think is like a physical manifestation of God, right? Or something that
directly connects us to God? I think most of us would think
of the תורה. Torah. So I hear that thought.
Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara starts with a new point.
Let's take a look. אימיה דרב זוטרא בר טוביה, Imeih d'Rav Zutra
bar Tuvia, the mother of רב זוטרא בר טוביה, Rav Zutra bar
Tuvia, כתבינהו לנכסה ktavin'hu l'nechasah
to רב טוביה. Rav Tuvia. So since we talked about giving away
all your נכסים, nechasim, here's somebody who gave away all her נכסים
nechasim presumably on a deathbed. Okay? So she gave and wrote away
all of her נכסים nechasim to רב זוטרא בר טוביה, Rav Zutra
bar Tuvia, her son, this רב זוטרא. Rav Zutra. דבעיא למינסביה. D'ba'aya
l'minsaveih.
Now this was not a case, oh I'm sorry if I said
שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera I misspoke. This is on back to the
מברחת mivra'chat case. Remember the מברחת mivra'chat case, the woman who gives
away all of her property because she's going to get married and
she wants to protect it
from her husband's access to it. So she wrote all of her
property to her son because she was going to get married presumably
a second marriage, בעיא למינסביה לרב זוטרא. ba'aya l'minsaveih l'Rav Zutra. She
wanted to marry רב זוטרא. Rav Zutra. Okay? So this was the
son that she had with this guy
טוביה. Tuvia. Okay. So
here's the woman
unnamed like many women. Okay. And here's her first husband טוביה. Tuvia.
And this guy and... And the son was what's his name? רב
זוטרא בר טוביה, Rav Zutra bar Tuvia, right, רב זוטרא
בר טוביה. Rav Zutra bar Tuvia. And she's going to get married,
he died. She's going to get married to רב זביד. Rav Zivid.
And she wants to protect her property from רב זביד, Rav Zivid,
so she basically writes all of her property to רב זוטרא בר
טוביה, Rav Zutra bar Tuvia, to her son, to her son. Okay,
so, אינסבא דגירשה. Insuva digirsha. So she married רב זביד Rav Zivid
and then lo and behold it was pretty smart on her account,
maybe she realized that there was, you know, what do they say,
a second marriage is a triumph of hope over experience?
So anyway,
so she realized you know it's a second marriage, you know you
gotta be careful, and lo and behold it didn't last and she
got divorced. So now she wants her property back. Okay, she managed
to protect it from רב זביד Rav Zivid and now she wants
her property back
from her
son, רב
זוטרא. Rav Zutra. Okay. So, okay, אתו לקמיה דרב ביבי בר אביי.
Atu lekamei deRav Bibi bar Abaye. So he came in front of
רב ביבי בר אביי. Rav Bibi bar Abaye. אמר משום דאינסבא הוא
ואינסבא. Amar mishum d'insuba hu v'insuba. So he was not dealing with
this whole מברחת Mavrasas category. He said, Look, she wrote it to
her son because she was going to get married and she got
married, so her son owns it. Meaning, he understood this not at
all to protect it that she would want it back; he understood
this as she was selling because of the marriage which meant like,
in the case that I get married to רב זביד, Rav Zivid,
I'll have my I guess my property with my new husband and
therefore I want you, my son from my old marriage, to get
my current property. Like he read it very, very differently. Not to
protect the property, but like it was a gift to the son
on the condition that she got married. So she got married, so
let the son keep it. אמר ליה רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע,
Amar lei Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua, so רב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua said to this רב ביבי, Rav
Bibi, משום דאתו ממולאי, Mishum d'atu miMulai,
you come from this place ממולאי, Mulai, which apparently is the רשב״ם
Rashbam says is the place where you know the
sons of עלי Eli come from, הכהן. Hakohen. So, and,
yeah,
so you come from this family or from this place, אמריתו מילי
מולייתא. Amrisu milei mulaysa. You say like blemished words. Okay, obviously some
play on words here. It says you know you say such stupid
ideas because you come from this place. So, even, I mean what
a stupid idea. אפילו למאן דאמר מברחת קני, Afilu leman d'amar mavrasas
kani, even according to the opinion that if somebody is hiding away
their property, the person who receives it takes possession of it—meaning this
is a case of מברחת. Mavrasas. She was doing it to protect
it from her husband. Okay? Like, so therefore, so even, and there
are some people that say that the person who receives the gift
of a מברחת, Mavrasas, the receiver really does own it. But that
is הני מילי היכא דלא גליא דעתה. Hani mili heicha d'lo galya
da'ata.
That's when the person writing it away isn't, isn't articulating,
expressing clearly that they're doing it to protect their property. Remember we
did that before, somebody just writes away all their property, okay, and
doesn't say why. We know that the person is getting married tomorrow;
they wrote away all their property to their son today. So the
discussion yesterday was if all of the property was written away, nothing
was left over, we, we don't interpret it as a real gift,
it's just a way to protect the property. So that actually was
debated, we didn't discuss that in the גמרא, Gemara, but in another
גמרא Gemara it's debated whether if you don't say why you're doing
it and it's all your property, do we read it as מברחת
Mavrasas or do we read it as a real gift? So he's
saying, fine, that's a debate you could have if it wasn't articulated
why you were doing it. But in this case apparently she expressly
said, I am giving you all my property because I'm about to
get married. And that was making it clear that it was just
a purpose of מברחת Mavrasas to protect it. Okay, so אפילו למאן
דאמר מברחת קני הני מילי היכא דלא גליא דעתה. Afilu leman d'amar
mavrasas kani hani mili heicha d'lo galya da'ata.
That's when the woman is not revealing her thinking. אבל הכא גליא
דעתה דמשום אינסבא הוא. Aval hacha galya da'ata d'mishum insuba hu.
Here apparently she made it clear, she said, I'm giving it to
you because I'm about to get married. ואינסבא ואיגירשא. Ve'insuba ve'igirsha.
So she was married and then she got divorced, so she gets
it back. It was all there just to be protected. Okay, so
basically the way you do a מברחת Mavrasas is either what we
said yesterday, all the property—now some people disagree, maybe even that doesn't
work, we'll just read it straight as a gift—but if you're explicit
about it and you say, I'm doing it because I'm about to
get married and I want to protect my property, then obviously then
it's in this category of מברחת. Mavrasas. And once you say that,
it could work even if it's not all your property, even if
it's 90% of your property, 50% of your property. You're saying, I
want to protect this and that's why I'm giving it to you,
and that makes it a מברחת. Mavrasas. Now one second, how does
this category of מברחת Mavrasas work? We mentioned this yesterday. Like make
up your mind. Either it's not a gift and then the husband
does get it, or it is a gift and then you can't
get it back. Like, so how do you sort of have this
middle... It's basically like it's a gift until I no longer need
it to be a gift and then I'm going to take it
back. Which raises also the question of like while she's married to
רב זביד, Rav Zvid, does רב יהודה בר טובי Rav Yehuda bar
Tuva get to eat the פירות, peiros, right? Is this like a
temporary ownership for him or once she gets divorced is it retroactively
wasn't his at all, right? How do you exactly conceptualize that? So
take a look at this two very interesting תוספות. Tosafos. First let's
first do אפילו למאן דאמר מברחת קנה. afilu l'man d'amar mavrachas kana.
תוספות Tosafos says צריך לומר דבמקצת הנכסים. tzarich lomar d'bemiktzas hanechasim. So
if it was כל הנכסים kol hanechasim you wouldn't have to know
he's claiming like nobody would have had a problem with it. אי
בכל הנכסים פשיטא דלא קנה ee bechol hanechasim p'shita d'lo kana כדמוכח
בפרק כל האישה שנפלו kid'muchach beperekh Kol Ha'isha Shenafelu דלא פליגי אלא
במקצת נכסים אבל בכל נכסים לא פליגי. d'lo pligi ella bemiktzas nechasim
aval bechol nechasim lo pligi. So not like I said, right, that
there was a debate even כל נכסים. kol hanechasim. תוספות Tosafos says
no, if it's כל נכסים kol hanechasim like we said yesterday everybody
agrees that you don't have to be explicit, that it works. That's
what we said yesterday. If it's מקצת נכסים miktzas nechasim then we
could debate whether or not it works but then if you're explicit
and you reveal that that's your intent it does work. Okay so
that's point number one. This question about what's the when when do
we interpret it to be מברחת mavrachas and when not. But now
let's look at the next תוספות. Tosafos. גלי דעתא דמשום דמינסבא הוא
ואיצטריך למיגרשה. galei da'ata d'mishum d'minsava hu v'itztariych l'migarsha.
So it was clear she was doing it to protect her property
when she got married. She got married, she got divorced, now give
it back to her. וכן גורס ר''ח דאינו נראה לר''י דהא משמע
דהוי טעמא משום דמגרשה. v'chen gores R"Ch d'eino nireh l'R"Y d'ha mashma
d'havi ta'ama mishum d'migarsha. He says
why did it have to say she got married and divorced and
now give it back to her? Let's say she didn't get divorced
yet from רב זביד. Rav Zvid. So who owns it? Right? So
does she own it but it's protected from רב זביד Rav Zvid
or she doesn't own it during the time that she's married. So
he says so if you have the גירסא girsa she got divorced
it sounds like while she's married to רב זביד Rav Zvid she
didn't own it. Okay. But the ר''י Ri says no even while
she's married she owns it. She owns it but it's protected. Okay.
אבל אם הייתה תחת בעלה... aval im haysa tachas ba'ala...
the גירסא girsa of the ר''ח R"Ch sounds like it's only because
she got divorced and would imply אבל אם הייתה תחת בעלה קנה.
aval im haysa tachas ba'ala kana. So that would make it sound
that while she's married to רב זביד Rav Zvid she doesn't own
it. ובפרק האישה שנפלו משמע דאפילו כשהיא תחת בעלה לא קנינהו לוקח.
u'veperekh Ha'isha Shenafelu mashma d'afilu k'shehi tachas ba'ala lo kaninhu loke'ach. Okay
but in another גמרא Gemara it sounds like even while she's married
the receiver does not own it and it still belongs to her.
Okay. Then I'm going to just skip the quote and let's read
it. Okay. דפריך התם וכי מאחר דלא קנינהו לוקח ליקנינהו בעל. d'parich
hasam v'chi me'acher d'lo kaninhu loke'ach likninhu ba'al.
If the purchaser doesn't really own it why doesn't the husband own
it? So that sounds like while she's married the husband doesn't own
it. But the גמרא Gemara says but okay but if the receiver
doesn't own it then how do you have it's not owned by
the receiver or by the husband? Like it's got to be one
or the other. How does she own it in a way that
it's protected from the husband? That's exactly what we want to know.
The גמרא Gemara there asks that. What's the גמרא's Gemara answer? The
גמרא Gemara says ומשני תקנתא דרבנן שעשוה כגון שמכרתן u'mishni takanta d'rabbanan
she'asuha kegon shemchartan
which is really the keywords we were missing. You know what? You're
right. There's no logic how it could work. Either it belongs to
רב זוטרא Rav Zutra or belongs to רב זביד. Rav Zvid. And
the גמרא Gemara says but the reality is we are just it
belongs to her, it does not belong to רב זביד Rav Zvid
even when she's married to רב זביד, Rav Zvid, but it doesn't
it doesn't belong to רב זוטרא Rav Zutra either. We are making
it as if רב זוטרא Rav Zutra owns it to help her
protect it but רב זוטרא Rav Zutra doesn't really own it. Okay
so this is תוספות Tosafos number one is even while she's married
she owns it. The husband does not own it. How conceptually does
it work that she owns it? There's really no good logic. Okay
but for the the rabbis created this institution to allow her to
protect her property and made it as if it was owned by
the person she gave it to. When it comes to questions does
her husband own it we pretend it's owned by the person she
gave it to but in fact it's really owned by her. It's
owned by her in a protected way. Okay so this is the
last line of the תוספות. Tosafos. מיהו יש לומר דמכל מקום ליהוי
לא קנה בעל ולוקח. mihu yesh lomar d'micol makom lihavei lo kana
ba'al v'loke'ach.
So fine. Neither owns. She owns it. Okay. Even while she's married
she owns it. מכל מקום ברשות מקבל מתנה הם עד שתתגרש. micol
makom birshus mekabel matana heim ad shetisgaresh. The this person still has
some control over it. So תוספות Tosafos doesn't spell out the issue
of פירות peiros but that might be his point. Okay so that's
sort of left unclear, right, who benefits from it during that interval.
But it's a fascinating institution, מברחת. mavrachas. It's sort of like a
sort of like
a 401k or something. Right. You can't touch it but it's yours.
Right. And nobody else can touch it. Right. Right. Right. Right. You
sign it over to the brokerage firm so they have control over
it. Exactly. It's some protected trust. So if you have the גירסא
girsa she got divorced it would sound like רב זביד Rav Zvid
owned it, I'm sorry, excuse me, not רב זביד, that רב זוטרא
owned it until she got divorced and תוספות Tosafos says that's actually
not true. From another גמרא Gemara it's clear that neither does her
husband own it. nor does the son own it from the very
get-go she owns it. Okay. Is she independent after marriage?
Yeah, maybe, it's a good question. Like what does that mean? Like
you know what does that mean? So to what degree is it
רב זוטרא *Rav Zutra* even in this sort of fiction? Is it
his that he gets the fruits? Is it his that it prevents
her from selling it? Like those are really important questions that תוספות
*Tosafot* does not spell out. I was trying, I was thinking about
the comparison between that and the property that a woman brings into
a marriage. Right, where the husband gets the fruits, who gets the
fruits? Right, who gets the fruits? Right, so I agree with you,
meaning the basic, well there's two differences. If he were to die
רב זוטרא *Rav Zutra* wouldn't inherit her. That's a very important point.
But you're right, presumably she's also trying to protect it against him
getting the fruit. Okay, so therefore you would logically think that she
gets the fruit, right? I don't know, I'd have to check that
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, okay? But our version of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
makes it sound like רב זוטרא *Rav Zutra* owns it until she
gets divorced, if you have the word מדרשא *midarsha*, and תוספות *Tosafot*
says no, no, no, even while she's married to רב זוטרא *Rav
Zutra* she owns it. Okay, again what that means in terms of
the fruit or not is not being spelled out. Yeah, I just
wanted to make, so the lawsuit after the divorce is between the
mother and the son. Exactly. Exactly. רב זוטרא *Rav Zutra* was trying
to hold onto the property. Right, right, I didn't spell that out.
Yes. After she got divorced, רב זוטרא *Rav Zutra* was trying to
hold onto the property and the question was whether the mother could
get it back. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this. Exactly. Okay, אימי דרמי בר חמא *Aimei de'Rami bar Chama*, another
story about mothers and their rabbinic sons. אימי דרמי בר חמא *Aimei
de'Rami bar Chama*, the mother of רמי בר חמא *Rami bar Chama*,
באורתא כתבתינהו לנכסה לרמי בר חמא *be'ursa kasivnah lenachasei le'Rami bar Chama*.
In the evening, apparently this was the case of a שכיב מרע
sh’chiv mera *shechiv mera*, she was going to die and she gifted
all of her property to her son, רמי בר חמא *Rami bar
Chama*. בצפרא B'tzafra *betzafra*, the next morning, כתבתינהו לרב עוקבא בר חמא
*kasivnah le'Rav Ukva bar Chama*. She wrote it over to her other
son, רב עוקבא בר חמא *Rav Ukva bar Chama*. Apparently this was
the wife of חמא *Chama*, okay. So now the question is which
gift is binding? The one last night or the one in the
morning? So you guys should remember that. What's the הלכה halacha. *halacha*,
which one is binding? The last one. The last one. The last
will and testament. דייתיקי מבטלת דייתיקי dayatiki mevateles dayatiki. *dayatiki mevateles dayatiki*.
But apparently that was not universally agreed. And here's where it's going
to get fought out. Okay, so אתא רמי בר חמא לקמיה דרב
ששת *ata Rami bar Chama kammei de'Rav Sheshet*. So רמי בר חמא
*Rami bar Chama* who was the first recipient came to רב ששת
Rav Sheshet *Rav Sheshet*. אוקמיה בנכסי *ukma benechsei*. So he let him
say, okay fine, he awarded it to him. אתא רב עוקבא בר
חמא *ata Rav Ukva bar Chama*, so רב עוקבא *Rav Ukva* who
was the second recipient went לקמיה דרב נחמן *kammei de'Rav Nachman*, in
front of רב נחמן Rav Nachman *Rav Nachman*. אוקמיה בנכסי *ukma benechsei*.
רב נחמן Rav Nachman. *Rav Nachman* awarded it to רב עוקבא *Rav
Ukva*. I don't know if they were doing, what's it called, venue
shopping or what's it called, forum shopping. Maybe they knew exactly which
rabbi held which way about this. Anyway, אתא רב ששת לקמיה דרב
נחמן *ata Rav Sheshet kammei de'Rav Nachman*. So רב ששת *Rav Sheshet*
who was the one who was the first פוסק *posek*, who רב
נחמן Rav Nachman. *Rav Nachman* had ruled against, went to רב נחמן
Rav Nachman *Rav Nachman*. אמר ליה Amar lei, מאי טעמא אוקמיה מר
לרב עוקבא בר חמא *amar lei mai ta'ama ukmia mar le'Rav Ukva
bar Chama*? Why are you giving it to my brother who was
the second recipient? אי משום דהדר בה *imi mishum dehadrabah*, if we
say that oh maybe my mom retracted it. רב ששת *Rav Sheshet*
is the first פוסק *posek*. Oh he's the first פוסק *posek*, not
the first recipient. Thank you, thank you. Okay, so רב ששת *Rav
Sheshet* the first פוסק *posek* went to רב נחמן Rav Nachman *Rav
Nachman* and said why did you give it to רב עוקבא בר
חמא *Rav Ukva bar Chama*? Right, thank you. So I was, I
gave it to the first recipients. You gave it to the second.
Why did you give it to the second? אי משום דהדר בה
*imi mishum dehadrabah* because you think that maybe the mother like retracted
it, ושכיבא
*v'shchivah*, but she died. So why is it relevant? So רב ששת
*Rav Sheshet* assumed that the idea of a שכיב מרע sh’chiv mera.
*shechiv mera*, right, can negate their gift is only if עמד חוזר
amad chozer. *amad chozer*. If they get better, it gets reversed. But
if they die, they can't reverse a first gift for a second
gift. All they can do is they've given their gift on the
condition that they're going to die. So if they don't die and
they get better then it's null and void. That was in the
משנה mishnah *Mishnah* basically, right? I mean or that's what we've been
saying all along. עמד חוזר amad chozer. *amad chozer*. The idea that
if they're going to, if they eventually die from this illness they
can write a second gift that supersedes the first, that's not so
clear. Right, if you think about it, it's not the same logic,
right? They gave it on the assumption they would die. Why should
that mean that they have the right to retract before they die
and give it to somebody else? What they think they're not going
to die, change your mind. Right, I mean exactly. What? They say
they were under duress and stuff. Right,
there could be other considerations. But it's the basic fact that the
gift had some stip, like some
implicit condition. It's the implicit condition that has it's going to be
binding if I die but if I get better then I want
this, I want to start fresh. That's one thing. To say that
it's good until I decide to give it to someone else and
I have the right to constantly change my mind until the moment
I die, that's not an obvious, that's not obvious. So he said
look, she died, so the first gift is binding. Why should the
second one supersede the first? Okay, אמר ליה הכי אמר שמואל Hachi
amar Shmuel. *amar lei hachi amar Shmuel*, no here's what שמואל Shmuel
*Shmuel* says. כל שאילו עמד חוזר Kol she’ilu amad chozer. *kol she'ilu
amad chozer*, anybody who's in a position that were they to get
better— The right to constantly change my mind until the moment I
die. That’s not an obvious, that’s not obvious. So he said, look,
she died, so it’s the first gift that’s binding. Why should the
second one supersede it? Okay. אמר ליה, הכי אמר שמואל. No, here’s
what Shmuel says: כל שאילו עמד חוזר. amad chozer, Anybody who’s in
a position that were they to get better the gift would be
voided, which means it’s a gift of a שכיב מרע shchiv mera,
and it’s because they’re anticipating dying. So in that type of a
case, חוזר במתנתו chozer b’matnato has a right to retract the gift
and to give it to somebody else. Okay? While they're in this
state of dying, they're sort of like the last will and testament,
as we said before, is only because it's the last one, which
means that you can constantly be reconsidering. And everybody's, I guess people
are, you know, what we're saying is a person's in a frame
of mind that they want to have the ability, they're divesting their
property and they want to have the ability to constantly reassess and
retweak it until the last moment. Okay? But that's a חידוש chiddush
that we say that they're given that right to constantly, you know,
retract and redistribute. Okay, so that is the principle, but here's where
we're really debating it. So now there was a pushback. The גמרא
Gemara says, רב ששת says one minute, אימר דאמר שמואל לעצמו. eimar
d’amar Shmuel l’atzmo. מהו? mahu? Maybe Shmuel just said that the same
way if the guy got better it's voided, if he could just
say forget it, I'm retracting my will altogether and I'm going to
let my kids inherit. So he has the right maybe to retract
completely, to void the will and to just keep it for himself.
But that's not the same as saying that he can actually, you
know, have a different will supersede it. Right? So voiding the will
is more similar to getting better. If you get better, it's voided.
If you void it, you void it. Okay, but that's different than
saying that you can gift it to somebody else and have a
later one supersede an earlier one. So he said, ולאחר מי אמר?
ul’acher mi amar? אמר ליה, he said back, בפירוש אמר שמואל, b’feyrush
amar Shmuel, I'm sorry, Shmuel said explicitly, בין לעצמו בין לאחר. bein
l’atzmo bein l’acher.
No, you do have a right to constantly, you know, issue a
later will and testament that supersedes the earlier one. So that idea
that we said before, דיאתיקי מבטלת דיאתיקי, diatiki m’vatela diatiki,
like a later will voids an earlier one, that's what is being
clarified here. And it was not universally assumed. And there is a
big, there is obviously a jump, just because if a guy gets
better doesn't mean that it's voided, doesn't mean that a later will
supersedes an earlier one if a will is considered as a type
of a binding type of a gift. Okay. And it clearly doesn't
mean that. But here we conclude that it does. I'm saying logically
just because you said if a guy got better got voided would
not, you could not have logically concluded that it means that a
later will supersedes an earlier one. But here that's what's being debated.
But here the conclusion of רב נחמן Rav Nachman and based on
שמואל and the way we פסקן pasken is that way. דיאתיקי מבטלת
דיאתיקי diatiki m’vatela diatiki
and that a later will voids an earlier one. Okay, וממאי? u’mimai?
What? Only when עמד? amad? Right? Only? No, even not עמד. amad.
If he were עמד, amad, it would be חוזר. chozer. Since you're
in a position where it was a מתנת שכיב מרע בכולה, matnat
sh’chiv mera b’chulah, so עמד חוזר. amad chozer, Therefore, you have the
right to have a later will supersede an earlier one, even if
the guy dies in the end. Right? The point being, and again
to remind us, there's two things. There's the real מתנת שכיב מרע,
matnat sh’chiv mera, and this is going to be important for what
we're about to learn, which is defined as כולה, chulah, okay, excuse
me, כל נכסיו. kol nechasav. And because it's a מתנת שכיב מרע,
matnat sh’chiv mera, it has the following implications: no קנין kinyan needed,
although we haven't really said that yet, I mean we've been talking
about it all along, right, that's that principle of דברי שכיב מרע
ככתובים וכמסורים דמי. divrei sh’chiv mera k’chtuvim u’k’msurim dami. Okay,
and the other implication is עמד חוזר. amad chozer Since it was
all given on the anticipation of death. Right? That's what a real
מתנת שכיב מרע matnat sh’chiv mera is. Okay? מקצת נכסיו miktzat nechasav
is really not a מתנת שכיב מרע. matnat sh’chiv mera. Even if
the guy is in his deathbed, הלכתית, halachically, it's a מתנת בריא.
matnat bari. It's no special institution, no special הלכה. halacha Okay? If
it's מקצת נכסיו. miktzat nechasav. And because of that, קנין kinyan is
needed
and עמד אינו חוזר. amad eino chozer. Why do we assume that
this case, this case with the two brothers and the mother changing
her mind, is מקצת נכסיו? miktzat nechasav? No, it's כולה. chulah. It's
a real שכיב מרע. shchiv mera The point is anything that אם
עמד חוזר, im amad chozer, anything that's a real מתנת שכיב מרע,
matnat sh’chiv mera, which is כל נכסיו, kol nechasav, and the principle
would be עמד חוזר, chozer that it would be voided. So therefore,
the same way it would be voided if he gets better, a
later will supersedes an earlier one. Even if the person dies. But
it means it's all being given in the context of anticipating death.
Since all of this is in the context of anticipating death, and
that's why עמד חוזר, chozer it also allows for דיאתיקי, diatiki, right?
דיאתיקי מבטלת דיאתיקי. diatiki m’vatela diatiki. Or
the phrase that we used here was, what was the phrase that
we used here? כל שאילו עמד חוזר חוזר במתנתו. kol she’ilu amad
chozer chozer b’matnato. חוזר במתנתו. chozer b’matnato. But that's even potentially
could... Right, and
cause
if anyone for whom the הלכה halacha, would be אם עמד חוזר,
im amad chozer, anybody who is in this category, right, has the
right to override their will. But that would be, you know, even
if they die. Okay? At the earlier conclusion was that no, once
you make that decision, you can't, right. So now what we have
said is that these are separate points, right? First you get that,
you can
reverse, you can reverse the, you know, and you can override even
if the guy winds up dying, then the second will is the
binding one. And that's what happened here. She died and it was
given to the second son, not the first son. The second will
was binding. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara, says like this. אימיה
דרב עמרם חסידא, Imeih de-Rav Amram Chasida, the mother of רב עמרם
חסידא, Rav Amram Chasida, הוה לה מלוגא דשטרי hava lah meluga de-shatari
she had a satchel full of שטרי, shatari, which I like, you
know, like documents of debt that people owed her, okay? And remember,
they are שטרי shatari can also be given in a מתנת שכיב
מרע matnat shchiv mera if you remember that, okay? כי קא שכיבא
ki ka shechiva as she was dying, אמרה amra
she said, ליהווי לעמרם ברי le-havei le-Amram beri let them be to
עמרם Amram my son. אתו אחוה לקמיה דרב נחמן atu achvaih lekameih
de-Rav Nachman
so the brothers came to רב נחמן. Rav Nachman אמרו ליה amru
leih
they said to him, הא לא משך ha lo mashach he didn't
get it because he didn't do a קנין, kinyan, okay? Now by
the way, let's just pause for a second. Do you think it
would have required a קנין kinyan or not? What do you think?
No,
I would say no. Is it a מתנת שכיב מרע? matnat shchiv
mera? Yeah. How do you know it's a מתנת שכיב מרע? matnat
shchiv mera? What determines whether it's a מתנת שכיב מרע? matnat shchiv
mera? It's the all. So so
presumably a satchel of שטרי shatari is not the entirety of her
possessions. So actually you understand their point. This isn't a real מתנה.
matana. Yes, my mom was dying but it wasn't halachically a מתנת
שכיב מרע matnat shchiv mera and he didn't do a קנין kinyan
on it, right? Okay. So אמר
להו amar lehu
he said to them, דברי שכיב מרע ככתובין וכמסורין דמו divrei shchiv
mera kich-tuvin u-k-mesurin damu no, they're like that they are already handed
over. Now what does that mean? So if you take a look
at the at the רשב"ם, Rashbam, he says, where was he?
Somewhere he says, oh, if you look at the רשב"ם Rashbam two
lines from the bottom, he says, כגון שקנו מידה kegon she-kanu mi-yadah
which obviously like the מהרש"א Maharsha doesn't know why he's saying that.
Whole point is they didn't do a קנין. kinyan. אי נמי ei
nami he says, בלא קנין וכגון דלא שיירי מידי. belo kinyan ve-kegon
delo shayrei midi.
So he says see Rabbi Dov you're right in the end. He
says, though it's not פשט pshat but we're almost forced to say
it, you have to assume that that's all of her possessions. Her
entire possessions was the satchel of שטרי. shatari. But here's an important
point that we have to realize because all along I've been not
fooling you but like haven't been pointing out something. This הלכה, halacha.
no קנין kinyan needed, דברי שכיב מרע ככתובין וכמסורין דמו divrei shchiv
mera kich-tuvin u-k-mesurin damu
has never been said explicitly in any משנה mishnah or even in
the גמרא Gemara yet. The משנה mishnah spoke about, if you remember
the משנה's mishnah distinction between כל נכסיו kol nechasav and מקצת נכסיו
miktzat nechasav was whether whether it would be voided if the guy
got better. The משנה mishna discussed this differently about whether it would
be voided. The idea, this big idea about a שכיב מרע, shchiv
mera you know when you go to ישיבות, yeshivot, when I was
on ישיבות yeshivot the big חידוש chiddush about שכיב מרע shchiv mera
is not that if they get better it's voided. Yes, everyone knows
that הלכה. halacha. But the big חידוש chiddush of שכיב מרע shachiv
mera oh, דברי שכיב מרע ככתובין וכמסורין דמו, divrei shchiv mera kich-tuvin
u-k-mesurin damu, right? Right, even the words he said is a קנין.
kinyan. You know what, the first time that was said here was
who said it? רב נחמן. Rav Nachman רב נחמן Rav Nachman. is
the first person to say that. You could have read the entire
משניות mishnayot and the entire גמרא up to this point and have
said that a שכיב מרע needs to do a קנין kinyan like
everybody else on the planet, okay? There's none no idea that you
don't have to do a קנין. kinyan. It's just that you could
retract it
if you get better. It's רב נחמן Rav Nachman that says no,
no קנין kinyan needed, the words set the קנין, kinyan, okay? And
that's where and this is where he's saying it. So we have
to assume it is a case of all of the possessions that
put it in this category and here we are introducing the idea
that it is only that it can be done without a קנין.
kinyan. Rabbi Lewis? Yes. Is this word מלוגא דשטרי meluga de-shatari is
that the same as נכסי מלוג? nichsei melog? Oh, that's an interesting
question. Could be. I don't know I don't know exactly if that's
the case נכסי מלוג nichsei melog means it's in a satchel or
something. Yeah, I don't know I'd have to look up I'd have
to look up what the etymology of both of those words are.
Okay, okay now, אחתיה דרב טובי בר רב מתנה. achateih de-Rav Tuvi
bar Rav Mattana. Now the brother of רב טובי בר רב מתנה...
Rav Tuvi bar Rav Mattana
no, the sister of רב טובי בר רב מתנה. Rav Tuvy bar
Rav Matna All of these cases are women related to rabbis. Like
it's a fascinating little collection of stories here, nameless, okay? The sister
of רב טובי בר רב מתנה matana. כתבינהו לנכסה. katvinhu le-nichsah. The
brother of רב טובי בר רב מתנה
so she wrote over all of her property to her brother here.
בצפרא in the morning ולפניא L'fanya in the evening אתא רב אחדבוי
בר מתנה ata Rav Achadvo'i bar Matna
this guy's brother presumably her brother as well came to her ובכה
uvacha and cried ואמר לה v'amar lah said to her השתא אמרי
מר צורבא מרבנן ומר לאו צורבא מרבנן. hasa amri mar tzurba m'rabanan
u'mar lav tzurba m'rabanan. Now people will say since you gave it
all to my brother
people's going to say מר צורבא מרבנן ומר לאו צורבא מרבנן mar
tzurba m'rabanan u'mar lav tzurba m'rabanan why did she give it all
to brother one and not to brother two? It must be brother
one was the real צורבא מרבנן tzurba m'rabanan and brother two isn't.
So חס ושלום chas v'shalom that I care about money but what
I care about is that it's going to make me look like
in people's eyes like I'm not a צורבא מרבנן tzurba m'rabanan why
did you disinherit me? He was a crybaby and looks how sometimes
complaining works. כתבינהו להלך kasvinuhu l'halach
so she wrote all of it over to the guy number two.
She didn't just equally divide it she wrote it all to the
second one. אתא לקמיה דרב נחמן ata l'kamei d'Rav Nachman came to
רב נחמן rav nachman: אמר לו הכי אמר שמואל amar lo hachi
amar Shmuel כל שהוא עמד חוזר חוזר במתנתו. kol she'hu amad chozer
chozer b'matnaso. Since
since it was a מתנת שכיב מרע matnas sh'chiv mera and since
if she would have gotten better it would have all been voided
so therefore she has a right to change her will and to
retract and she retracted it from brother one she gave it to
brother two brother two gets it all. אחותיה דרב דימי בר יוסף
ahosteh d'Rav Dimi bar Yosef the brother of רב דימי בר יוסף
Rav Dimi bar Yosef the sister of... this story add to the
one we just had? I was just thinking. What? What did we
learn new? This story add to the one we just had? Nothing.
No complaining crying sometimes works. Yeah I think and that yeah that's
really been entrenched as the הלכה. halacha I don't think it adds
any point other than that look this is the way that the
פסק psak is being entrenched. That's my sense. אחותיה דרב דימי בר
יוסף ahosteh d'Rav Dimi bar Yosef the brother of רב דימי בר
יוסף Rav Dimi bar Yosef the sister of רב דימי בר יוסף
Rav Dimi bar Yosef הוי לה
פסקא דפרדיסא havi lah piska d'pardisa she had a little plot of
an orchard. כל אימת דהויא חלשא kol eimas d'havya chalsha anytime she
got sick הויא מקניא ליה ניהליה havya maknya leh nihaleh she would
be מקנה makneh to him she would grant you know give it
to him as a מתנת שכיב מרע matnas sh'chiv mera gift. Presumably
this was all of her property. So and then what would happen?
דקיימא d'kayma then she would get better הויא הדרא havya hadra so
it would be voided she would retract. So he got a little
bit fed up. The last 10 years she's been on the verge
of dying so every time she dies she puts me in her
will then she gets better whatever. What is it? Jonathan Sarna said
what was that line about the Jewish people are the ever dying
nation.
So anyway זימנא חדא
חלשא zimna chada chalsha one time she got sick שלחה ליה shalcha
leh she said come to me and I want to transfer to
you property of this orchard. שלחה ליה תא קני shalcha leh ta
kani
come to me do a קנין kinyan and take possession of the
orchard because I'm afraid I'm about to die. שלח לה לא בעינא
shalach lah lo ba'ina no excuse me enough is enough I'm not
coming I have to learn in ישיבה yeshiva whatever I'm not schlepped
in there you'll probably just disappoint me and get better
anyway. שלחה ליה תא קני כל היכא דבעית shalcha leh ta kani
kol heicha d'ba'is look come do a קנין kinyan on it however
you want to do a קנין kinyan on it that'll make you
happy. So there's a way to do a קנין kinyan on it
that'll make him happy. What is it? אזל שייר וקנה מינה azal
shiyer v'kana minah he left over a tiny bit of the orchard
and he did a קנין kinyan on the rest. So then it
was a מתנת שכיב מרע במקצת matnas sh'chiv mera b'miktzas and therefore
she won't be able to retract even if she gets
better. Now of course she got better הדרא בה hadra bah she
retracted.
אתא לקמיה דרב נחמן ata l'kamei d'Rav Nachman so she came to
רב נחמן rav nachman, שלח ליה shalach leh so רב נחמן rav
nachman. called to whoever this was who was this? רב
דימי. Rav Dimi. Call to רב דימי Rav Dimi to come to
a בית דין. beis din. שלח ליה תא shalach leh ta come.
לא
אתא lo ata he didn't come. He didn't want to come to
her sister didn't want to come to רב נחמן. rav nachman. His
mother's sister? His sister, he was the sister. אמר מאי אייתי amar
mai aysei why should I come to the בית דין? beis din?
הא שייר וקנה מינה ha shiyer v'kana minah she left over a
little piece of the land at my instruction and I did a
קנין. kinyan. So because it was left over קצת ktzas of land
I did a קנין kinyan which I have to do because it's
במקצת b'miktzas and therefore אמר אינו חוזר amar einu chozer so why
do you want me to come? I should be able to keep
it. וקנה מינה v'kana minah שלח ליה shalach leh אי לא אתית
ei lo asis if you don't come מחינא לך בסילוא דלא מיבזע
דמא m'china lach b'silva d'lo mivza dama I will hit you with
a like with a with a nail that won't draw blood. What's
the nail that won't that won't show a mark which means basically
I'll put you in חרם. cherem. I'll beat you up but it
won't be externally visible I'll put you in חרם. cherem. אמר להו
amar lehu
so he came presumably. אמר להו לסבי amar lehu l'savi so רב
נחמן rav nachman now said to the witnesses
היכי הוה מעשה heichi havah ma'aseh tell me exactly what happened. אמרו
לו אמרה הכי amru lo amrah hachi here's what she said. Woah,
woah, I'm about to die! אוי אוי אוי, oy oy oy, I'm
about to die. Okay,
now the רשב"ם Rashbam said that he said it in particular when
her brother Rabini wasn't showing up, and she was saying, "I can't
believe it, I'm about to die, I'm never going to see him
again," etc. Now, you know, Rabini might have thought that the whole
thing was always because, you know, maybe she was always just trying
to get, you know, to see him, that she was constantly, you
know, dying or whatever and saying and calling him. But anyway, but
okay, but she said that, but the point was she was saying,
"אוי אוי אוי, oy oy oy, I'm about to die." So, why
is that relevant? So now we're going to come up with a
huge חידוש, chiddush, get ready for this, strap in your seatbelt. So
he said, אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to the witnesses, אם
כן, im kein, if that's the case, מצוה מחמת מיתה, metzaveh machmas
misa, she was giving her instructions on the because she was assuming
she was going to die. ומצוה מחמת מיתה חוזר, u'metzaveh machmas misa
chozer, and if you give your instructions because you assume you're going
to die, you also get to retract. So what it means, this
big line here between כל נכסיו kol nechasav and מקצת נכסיו, miktzas
nechasav, we are actually going to say that is not an uncrossable
line. Right. The other way you can become a מתנת שכיב מרע
matnas shchiv mera are two possibilities. You have מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas
shchiv mera, which is this category. מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shchiv mera
is either כל נכסיו, kol nechasav, which is what we've been saying,
or מקצת נכסיו miktzas nechasav with מצוה מחמת מיתה. metzaveh machmas misa.
But wait, אביי, Abaye, אביי Abaye says,
no, the difference is are you explicit? That is, that is the
point. If it's כל נכסיו, kol nechasav, the fact that this guy
is lying in his, in a sickbed, right, and it's כל נכסיו,
kol nechasav, makes us say it's מצוה מחמת מיתה metzaveh machmas misa
and a מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas shchiv mera. But also, if it's
מקצת נכסיו miktzas nechasav and the person is saying, "Oh my God,
I'm afraid I'm going to die," that also makes it a מתנת
שכיב מרע. matnas shchiv mera. It's only when you don't say anything
and it's מקצת נכסיו, miktzas nechasav, then even though you're in a
bed and you're ill or whatever, we say that that's look, a
person could be in their bed and ill and have a day
to live and is still conducting normal business, right? Just because a
person's in their deathbed doesn't mean that they're giving a will, right?
It could be normal business. So either it's מקצת נכסיו miktzas nechasav
or it's explicitly in the context that you say, "Oh my God,
I'm going to die, here's what I want to be done." Okay,
which by the way raises an interesting question. Let's say the person
isn't in a deathbed at all. Let's say the person is, I
gave you this example before, they're about to go ahead and do
some highly dangerous activity. "I'm going to run into this burning building
to try to save the child." And I say, "You know, if
I don't make it out, I'm afraid I might die, you know,
give this property to this person and this property to that person."
Is that this case of מקצת נכסיו miktzas nechasav and מצוה מחמת
מיתה? metzaveh machmas misa? It was certainly out of a fear of
death and whatever, but is that enough or does the guy also
have to be like in a deathbed? You know,
that's not so clear. Okay, but what we have now done is
we have completely, until now it was a very limited category, כל
נכסיו, kol nechasav, and you might remember the earlier גמרות, gemaros, is
it קרקע, karka, is it this, is it that, what defines כל
נכסיו? kol nechasav? Here, all you need is מצוה מחמת מיתה metzaveh
machmas misa and you can turn everything into a מתנת שכיב מרע.
matnas shchiv mera. Okay, so this is a big important idea. So
what is unclear about the person running into the building that's on
fire? Because the גמרא, because that person is about to engage in
an activity that's going to threaten their lives, but they're not in
the process of dying. The person in the deathbed is in the
process of dying, right? You understand the difference? Right. So maybe in
this case, what they're saying about, you said you could be totally
healthy and you're going to die... I asked whether that's true. Meaning
here, in both of these cases, the idea is you're in a
deathbed or you're in a sickbed which might be a deathbed, and
it's either כל נכסיו kol nechasav or מקצת miktzas plus מצוה מחמת
מיתה, metzaveh machmas misa, but in both of those cases, the person
is or might be in the process of dying. I'm asking let's
say somebody is מצוה מחמת מיתה metzaveh machmas misa and they're not
in the process of dying, but they might die in the next
few hours, okay, right? So I don't know, okay, yes. רשב"ם Rashbam
says something I think psychologically really interesting. He says that the person
who is making this claim explicit, היה מתאונן על
מיתתו, haya mitonen al mitato, he's an אונן onen for his own
death. In other words, he's in that in-between... what do I mean,
it's an interstitial... yeah, I mean it's a liminal state. Right.
Really interesting, don't you think? Yeah, he uses the word אונן, onen,
yeah, I could see that, that's interesting. You know what I mean?
It's like the other way, an אונן onen is between the death
and the process of healing and שבעה. shiva. It's an interesting thought,
I hadn't thought about that, yeah. Okay, so now the גמרא continues,
one more case. אתמר, itmar,
it was taught: מתנת שכיב מרע במקצת, matnas shchiv mera be'miktzas, okay,
where we're here in the מקצת נכסיו. miktzas nechasav. אמר רבא קמיה
דרב אבא משמיה דמר זוטרא בריה דרב נחמן דאמר משמיה דרב נחמן,
amar Rava kamei de'Rav Abba mishmei de'Mar Zutra brei de'Rav Nachman de'amar
mishmei de'Rav Nachman, this whole teaching... משמיה דרב נחמן mishmei de-rav nachman
הרי כמתנת ברי והרי כמתנת שכיב מרע. harei kematnas bari veharei kematnas
shachiv mera.
So until now we've assumed these two things: you need a קנין,
kinyan, עמד אינו חוזר. amad eino chozer. But now we're going to
question that. Here's a statement that it's partly like a מתנת ברי
matnas bari and partly like a מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas shachiv mera.
הרי כמתנת ברי שאם עמד אינו חוזר. harei kematnas bari she'im amad
eino chozer. It's like a מתנת ברי, matnas bari, עמד אינו חוזר.
amad eino chozer. That we have clear, right? The מקצת, miktzas, even
if you get better, it stays binding. הרי כמתנת שכיב מרע דלא
בעי קנין. harei kematnas shachiv mera dlo bei kinyan.
Once we introduce a מימרא meimra that a קנין kinyan wasn't necessary,
now we're going to make a claim, oh you know what, there
maybe here a קנין kinyan isn't necessary either. As long as the
guy's in the deathbed, maybe there's a difference of, does it get
retracted or not if he gets better, but maybe there's no קנין
kinyan necessary here. Okay, so we're questioning this basic division. Okay, but
now things are going to get realigned. אמר ליה רבא, amar leh
rava, so רבא rava said to these people who were saying this
in the name of רב נחמן: rav nachman. לאו אמינא לכו, lav
amina lacho, have I not said to you, לא תיפלו בוקי סריקי
ברב נחמן, lo tiplu buki seriki be-rav nachman, don't hang, I don't
know what they call what they translated, but don't hang like junk
on רב נחמן, rav nachman. how did they translate the words בוקי
סריקי? buki seriki? Don't hang empty pitchers on רב נחמן. rav nachman
Like don't attribute such nonsense to רב נחמן. rav nachman הכי אמר
רב נחמן, hachi amar rav nachman, this is what רב נחמן said:
הרי הוא כמתנת ברי ובעי קנין. harei hu kematnas bari u-vei kinyan.
No, no, no, we're going to keep things a clear line between
them. The same way עמד אינו חוזר, amad eino chozer, it's binding
even if he gets better, this is clearly in a מתנת ברי
matnas bari category and it needs a קנין. kinyan. So we've completely,
you know,
established very clear lines, rules here. First thing we introduced, which was
not clear earlier, was no קנין kinyan was needed for מתנת שכיב
מרע. matnas shachiv mera. Okay, because the משנה mishna. only discusses this.
This is the only sort of thing that's in the משנה. mishna.
The difference between עמד חוזר and אינו חוזר. eino chozer. What we
have done today is done a lot. First of all, we've added
the principle of
חוזר במתנתו, chozer be-matnaso, right? Which is דייתיקי מבטלת דייתיקי. Okay, that
we've added. That wasn't in the משנה. mishna. We've added this idea
that no קנין kinyan was needed. We've decided that מקצת נכסים miktzas
nechasim plus מצוה מחמת מיתה metzaveh machmas misa also makes it a
מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas shachiv mera, right? All of this stuff was
not in the משנה. mishna All the משנה mishna. said was כל
נכסיו עמד חוזר. kol nechasav amad chozer. This was the stuff in
the green was what was in the משנה. Okay, we've added all
of this. This issue that no קנין kinyan is needed, that מצוה
מחמת מיתה metzaveh machmas misa puts you in this category, and now
we're saying חוזר במתנתו, chozer be-matnaso, and now we're saying, oh, when
no קנין kinyan is needed, maybe no קנין kinyan is needed down
here either. That was one claim in the name of רב נחמן.
In the end, it's like no, we're going to keep this side
of the board, this line completely like a classic מתנת ברי. matnas
bari. And therefore we're going to insist that a קנין, kinyan, even
though we've said a קנין kinyan isn't needed up here, a קנין
kinyan is going to be needed down here. Okay? And that's what
רבא rava says. That is the real position of רב נחמן. Alright,
so
we'll continue with this tomorrow to like wrap this up but this
becomes the basics of מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas shachiv mera. So to
be continued. Right. חוזר means returns to the... the sale is voided.
Just to the right. All the way to the right. All the
way to that one right there. That's חוזר במתנתו. chozer be-matnaso. You
can retract your first gift and override it with a second gift.
Okay. All right. So we will continue. What רב נחמן says though
is treat it like a במקצת. bemiktzas. Treat it like a ברי.
bari. Like it's a real מתנה. And therefore it's not חוזר but
you need a קנין. kinyan. Right. But you have to say בפירוש.
be-ferush. Right. But what does רב נחמן hold regarding, it has to
be מצוה בפירוש. metzaveh be-ferush. Does that also? If you're מצוה בפירוש,
metzaveh be-ferush, then you get up to the top of the board.
Then you become a מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas shachiv mera. Right. Okay.
But
if it's במקצת bemiktzas בלא פירוש, belo ferush, then you're a standard
מתנת ברי. matnas bari. But you need a... but you need a
קנין. kinyan. Right. Well of course you're a מתנת ברי, matnas bari,
right, because you need a קנין. kinyan. All the special הלכה halacha.
of שכיב מרע is only what takes place on the top of
the board. On the top of the line. That's
the special הלכה. Okay. All right. To be continued
tomorrow.